<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon, preached before Sir Marmadvke Langdale at his entrance into Barvvick by I.K., a native of the same place, sometimes preacher of Gods word there.</title>
            <author>I. K., Native of the same place, sometimes preacher of Gods word there.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47122</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19010</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12730353</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12730353</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66448</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47122)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66448)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 694:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon, preached before Sir Marmadvke Langdale at his entrance into Barvvick by I.K., a native of the same place, sometimes preacher of Gods word there.</title>
                  <author>I. K., Native of the same place, sometimes preacher of Gods word there.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Langdale, Marmaduke Langdale, --  Baron, 1598?-1661.</term>
               <term>Death --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66448:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON, Preached before Sir <hi>MARMAD<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>KE LANGDALE</hi> At his entrance into BARVVICK.</p>
            <p>By <hi>I. K.</hi> a Native of the ſame place, ſometimes Preacher of Gods word there.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Hoſea, Chap. 3. verſ. 5.</bibl>
               <p>Afterward ſhall the children of Iſrael returne, and ſeeke the Lord their God, and David their King, and ſhall feare the Lord, and his goodneſſe in the latter dayes.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare, 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:66448:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:66448:2"/>
            <head>And <hi>Ieremiah</hi> lamented for <hi>Ioſiah, 2 Cron. 35.25.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE ſphere of this Text is Lamentation; the Poles whereon it mov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Ioſiah</hi> and <hi>Ieremiah:</hi> In the upper the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theriall part of this ſphere w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> ſee the bloud of <hi>Ioſiah;</hi> in the nether the watry hemiſphere, wee have the teares of <hi>Ieremiah.</hi> And as the cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall Spheres, have their firſt moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver above them: So is there in this Text a third perſon, the Spirit of God; who onely being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the King and the Prophet placed them heere in the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament of his word, and by this his Teſtimony hath conſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated the blood of <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> and the teares of <hi>Jeremiah</hi> into fixt Starres; wherein all men may reade their common condition, and Kingdomes calculate their owne Nativities and diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: So in this darke Sphere of Lamentation, <hi>Ioſiah</hi> dying, <hi>Ieremiah</hi> crying, wee finde yet the Spirit of God teſtifying; though in the cold Region of the revolting Iudah, both King and Prophet be eclypſed, the one by death, the other by ſorrow; yet are they heere caught up into the cleere Orbe of the Scripture <hi>(torres eruti deigne)</hi> and there memorated to all Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterities by the uncloudeable teſtimony of the ſpirit of God;<note place="margin">Zach. 3.2.</note> in whoſe ſight ſince the death of his Saints is precious,<note place="margin">Pſal 116.13.56.8.</note> and he puts all their teares into his bottle; therfore are theſe things noted in his booke, therefore are <hi>Ioſiah</hi> and <hi>Ieremiah</hi> recorded heere as Monuments, and their bloud and teares turned into Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies and Pearles, to make Bracelets to adorne the Spouſe of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Heere firſt wee ſee in Mourning and dying the condition of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:66448:3"/>
us all in this world, ſorrow and death play all our game. <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gemus, aut lugemur omnes in vicem:</hi> It is an hard queſtion, whether at our entring wee begin ſooner to weepe, or to dye. But in our progreſſe whereas dying hath no intervals, ſorrow ſeemes to admit ſome interludes, but in a wiſe mans apprehenſion they are but deluſions. Looke into the Stage of the world you ſhall ſee two ſerious Actors, the Dyer, and the Mourner: All the reſt play the foole, or the counterfeit; whereupon the judicious ſpectator,<note place="margin">Eccle. 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>Solomon,</hi> called out to laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anis,</hi> thou art mad, and to mirth, <hi>Quid fruſtra deciperis?</hi> And the great <hi>Iob</hi> ſayd of himſelfe,<note place="margin">Job 29.24.31.23.</note> if I laughed on them, they beleeved it not; ſo ſeldome did he, ſo little could he laugh, <hi>qui ſemper, quaſi tumentes ſuper ſe fluctus, timuit Deum,</hi> who thought continually he heard God, like the mighty billowes of the Sea rowling over his head: But the Sonne of God, <hi>quoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ò elle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai 53 3. Pſal. 88.15.</note> how oft did he impropriate the Title of <hi>vir dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> the man of ſorrowes? From my youth up thy terrours have I ſuffered with a troubled minde;<note place="margin">Luke 17 50.</note> and againe, I have a Baptiſme to be baptized withall, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and how am I ſtraightened till this be fulfilled? For well knew the Sonne it was the will of the Father, that ſorrow ſhould be the dyet and viands of man in the courſe of this life, where the feathers and downe wee reſt upon have their quills and thiſtles; the Roſe wee ſmell her pricks, the meate on our Tables cryes out to us, <hi>Mors in ollâ,</hi> there is death in the pot. This habitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſorrow (for the fits of worldly mirth, <hi>quamvis non intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtivis amaenitatibus,</hi> are but receſſes from it, and I neither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne every act of joy,<note place="margin">Gen. 35.18.</note> nor juſtifie every motion of ſorrow) this habituall ſorrow, from which <hi>Bennoni,</hi> the ſonne of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, was called <hi>Benjamin</hi> the ſonne of ſtrength, and by which the ſorrowfull <hi>Iabez</hi> became more honourable then all his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren;<note place="margin">1. Cron. 4 9.</note> this habituall ſorrow, I ſay this commanding ſadneſſe, this maſtred and well rayned penſiveneſſe, is wiſdome in the minde, valour in the heart, ſalt in the wit, diſcipline to the fleſh from whence there breakes forth a Majeſty in the very countenance. It is indeed the ballance of the ſoule, without which a light and empty heart, like an unpoyſed Barke, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:66448:3"/>
aloft to the flattry of the windes, which will quickly lay her low.</p>
            <p>But we have every where ſo many cauſes of the one of theſe two, ſorrow, that the other, death, might be jealous we forget him, and ſurprize us ſuddenly: if with the ſtatue of ſorrow in <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> the ſpirit of God had not erected alſo a monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of death in <hi>Ioſiah:</hi> and juſtly, for the ſame which <hi>David</hi> calls the valley of the ſhadow of death in the 23. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> he calls the valey of <hi>Baca</hi> in the 84. for ſorrow is ſaith <hi>Baſil,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſhadow of ſinne and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality: now, as if a man were placed ſo high aboue the earth, that night, the ſhadow of it could not reach to him, he ſhould have continuall day: ſo thoſe ſoules onely that have wrought ſo high, that the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the laſt point of this ſhadow of ſin, Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, is below their feete, thoſe have no ſorrow, unleſſe it be to looke downe upon us and ſee, <hi>quantâ ſub nocte jaceret no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>st <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a dies,</hi> in what a true night of lamentableneſſe we walke here on earth, which yet we thicken with groſſe conceits of falſe mirth; the beſt uſe then of naturall life, is the thinking on death: O that they were wiſe ſaith, <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32.29.</note> that they would conſider their latter end! <hi>Sion</hi> remembered not her later end, therefore ſhe came down wonderfully,<note place="margin">Lam. 1.9.</note> ſaith our <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie</hi> in this Lamentation, yea in ſpirituall life <hi>Paul</hi> deſired to know nothing here but Jeſus Chriſt, and him dying:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.2.</note> ſleepe like a Publican, takes exciſe of our life, onely the reſt of it is our owne: he that thinkes not on death is aſleepe: what wee deny to the one Brother the other takes away. O how I love thee thou meditation on death, ſince not time but thou meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt life and makeſt it mine! Through this narrow dark optick of the meditation on death; our eyes, help'd with the watry ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacles of teares pierce through the chryſtalline Heaven, and looke to eternall life: <hi>Iohn</hi> confeſſeth of <hi>Peter</hi> and himſelfe,<note place="margin">Jo. 20.10.</note> who ran to the Sepulchre, and preſently returned home, that they miſſed of that dignation which was afforded to <hi>Mary,</hi> who ſtayed there looking into the tombe, and weeping: her conſtant adhering to the Sepulchre had the honour to ſee the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Angels, and her weeping, the grace to heare the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:66448:4"/>
firſt ſalutation of her glorified ſaviour, who appoints ſaith <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſai</hi> to them that mourne,<note place="margin">Eſay. 61.3.</note> and gives them beauty for aſhes, the oile of joy for mourning, the garment of praiſe for the ſpirit of heavineſſe: thus are we taught in the firſt place by mourning in <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> and dying in <hi>Joſiah;</hi> how well mourning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes an holy ſoule, <hi>&amp; repente ut emoriantur humani loves,</hi> how ſuddenly death unthrones our mortall Gods.</p>
            <p>Mourning and Death were our firſt leſſon, and the ſecond is like unto it, mourning for the dead: Which mourning for the dead in the Text takes hold by this connexture, and of bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the dead in the verſe before, and he was buried among his Fathers Tombes, and they mourned for him: This teſtimony of the ſpirit of God gives ſufficient weight and reverence to the Doctrine. Howbeit in theſe miſerable times, under colour of reforming ſuperſtitious abuſes, decent and allowed expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of devotion are ſo endangered to be extirpated, that the piety heere enjoyned muſt ſo far enjoy the impiety of the age, as to have a few words beſtowed upon the poynt.</p>
            <p>Death is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a fatall debt, which wee owe to nature for living after our Father <hi>Adam</hi> and mourning a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall debt, which our children owe to us for dying before them; deny the living to mourne, and deny the dead are dead. The rude <hi>Laconian</hi> more reproved the indolency of the Stoick, when he anſwered him, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. My ſorrow is the flux of Nature: For the God of Nature is ſo carefull not to have this piety in mourning for the dead obliterated, that he hath twiſted it upon thoſe tender ſtrings of our naturall relations and affections, which wee feele to crack within our ſelves, when our friends heart ſtrings breake, and then our bowells towle their laſt knell. The firſt dyer was <hi>Abel, Abel</hi> the juſt, and his Father <hi>Adam</hi> mourned long for him, till by the birth of <hi>Seth</hi> he was comforted <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as by a mortall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, type of an eternall, ſaith <hi>Niſſen;</hi> noting that <hi>Abel,</hi> that is mourning, muſt continue with <hi>Adam</hi> till <hi>Seth, Achates</hi> muſt attend upon <hi>Æneas,</hi> till the reſurrection, when ſaith <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 21.4.</note> there ſhall be no more death nor ſorrow. Thoſe Timons that will neither retaine humanity in themſelves, nor indure it
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:66448:4"/>
in others, what thinke they of the Sonne of God? Whom this ſlinty wiſdome of theirs, and abſtracted Divinity could not withold from ſorrowing for the dead. No, he was Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator betwixt the living and the dead, and therefore as in his perſon he aſſumed our infirmities, ſo by his practice he juſtified this ſympathy of the living with the dead: He groaned in the ſpirit, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he troubled himſelfe, he wept,<note place="margin">Jo. 11.33.</note> both in complyance with <hi>Martha</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> his mourning, and for deſtitution of <hi>Lazarus</hi> his dying Friend.<note place="margin">Job 39.14.</note> This was the ſpirit of our Dove; not like the Oſtrich, that is hardned againſt her owne, as if they were not hers, and leaves them in the duſt, <hi>quia privavit eam Deus ſapientiâ,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob.</hi> becauſe God hath deprived her of wiſdome. Theſe vaine glorious contemners of ſorrow for the dead, would they waſh their horny eyes with teares might ſee, how death while they deny him one thing, ſorrow takes from them two, both their piety and their Friend: Truely theſe buryers of Nature alive are of the ſame veines with the Donatiſticall Circumcellions, though they have not ſo much of the bloud in them, and of the ſame dye, though they be not yet ſo deepe dipped.</p>
            <p>But they are not farther from humanity that are offended with mourning for the dead, then they are from Chriſtianity that quarrel with their burialls and funeralls: conſult the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, whereas burying is ſimply called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (the rich man dyed and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.22. Gen. 50.2.</note> was buried) the word which both the Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gint uſeth of Jacob in the old Teſtament, and <hi>Mathew</hi> in the new, of our Saviour is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.12.</note> which ſignifies not onely bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, but decent funeralls, and is compleated in that word which <hi>Luke</hi> uſeth of thoſe devout men who lamented greatly for <hi>Stephen,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Act. 8.2.</note> tooke care and order for his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall: <hi>Paul</hi> in joines that all things ſhould be done <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.40.</note> decently,<note place="margin">Ma. 15.43.</note> and <hi>Marke</hi> appropriates to <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea</hi> the ſtile of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the honourable <hi>Joſeph,</hi> becauſe of the ſolemne inhumation, <hi>decoravit honesto funere:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26, 10.</note> this care of burialls and charge of funeralls is by our Saviour called a good worke, by <hi>Iacob</hi> a deed of mercy, by <hi>Luke</hi> an Act of devotion,<note place="margin">Gen. 47, 29.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Act, 8, 2.</note> and <hi>Paul</hi> makes <hi>Ioſeph's</hi> charge concerning his bones an effect
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:66448:5"/>
of faith: then not to be needleſly long in ſhewing that bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall refers to the hope of the reſurection (and was ordained from God from the beginning,<note place="margin">In Act. 8.2.</note> ſaith <hi>Calvin,</hi> in honour to the body, to which the reſurrection is promiſed, and which, even after ſeperation, is <hi>candidatum reſurrectionis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian</hi>) our owne <hi>Ioſiah</hi> in his reformation of both Kingdomes was ſo religiouſly reſpective hereof,<note place="margin">2. King 23.18.</note> that he lookt among the tombes carefully, and would not ſuffer the bones of the Prophet to be diſturbed: yea Ieſus the bleſſed, yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, to day, and for ever the ſame, juſtified the coſtly, and therefore envied,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.12.13.</note> anoynting of his body under the name of <hi>Sepulchralis,</hi> a Funerall charge. I am ſure for the charge of that Funerall Oyntment, her Funerall Sermon ſhall laſt till the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall houre glaſſe of the world be run, and ſhall outlive all the long windy Sarments and Canons are bolted againſt burials and Funerall Sermons, <hi>vae tibi, miſer,</hi> ſayd <hi>Auguſtine</hi> of <hi>Iudas, bonus odor occidit te?</hi> The odour of a decent funerall is to a <hi>Iudas</hi> like the ſmell of the Angels perfume, that drove the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell away from <hi>Tobias.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tob. 8.3.</note> Doth any ſtartle at this illuſtration as Apocryphall? Let him looke into the Canonicall Scripture, he ſhall finde that at <hi>Moſes</hi> death God himſelfe preacht the Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Sermon,<note place="margin">Joſh. 1.2.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 34.6. Jude v. 9.</note> and he that buryed the body, he, ſaith the Text, was at leaſt an Angel, though the Devill contended againſt it, and diſputed about it. O miſerable abuſers of the name of Chriſtians! Indeed uncircumciſed Iewes, whoſe ſoules are too narrow to comprehend the relation of their owne bodies, which unfortunate veſſels as long as they have the ſalt in them, they can put to any luſtful or ſenſuall uſe, ſtill reſerving in themſelves ſpirituality forſooth (as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſaith the Valentini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans did) but as ſoone as they are parted from their ſoules, they count them no more then duſt and corruption, and the ſlight burialls they afford them but an humane formality, done in the remembrance of the naturall relation they had to the party a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live. Thus they proceede from Stoiciſme to Epicuriſme; firſt Phariſees, then Saduces.</p>
            <p>But you, beloved, conceive rightly of the myſtery which is your hope: the ſeperation and diſſolution of the body, though
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:66448:5"/>
it ſeem to nature like the irrecoverable falling drop of raine into the Sea, takes not away the naturall relation of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy which is twofold. One of the materiall body to it pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate ſoule, of which <hi>Iob</hi> ſayd,<note place="margin">Job 19.26.</note> though after my skin wormes deſtroy this body, yet in my fleſh ſhall I ſee God, whom I ſhall ſee for my ſelfe, and mine eyes ſhall behold, and not another, though my reines be conſumed within me. And <hi>Paul,</hi> this corruptible muſt put on incorruption,<note place="margin">Cor. 15.53.</note> this deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable, this numericall corruptible, arguing from the exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary cauſe the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> to all the faithfull; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine concluding from the finall cauſe to all men generally, wee muſt all appeare before the Tribunall of Chriſt, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one may receive in his body the things he hath done.<note place="margin">Cor. 5.10.</note> Whereupon, as <hi>Hierome</hi> reports, the Church of <hi>Aquileia,</hi> that when they pronounce the beliefe (obſerve that of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient the beliefe was rehearſed in the Congregations, for viſible confeſſion of the faith is the forme of the viſible Church) ſpeake that Article emphatically, of this fleſh, pointing every one to his forehead: Of the latter relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the myſticall body, which is the body and ſoule of the believer to Chriſt, know you not, ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.15.</note> that your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are the members of Chriſt? And againe, this is a great myſtery, but I ſpeake of Chriſt and the Church:<note place="margin">Eph. 5.31.</note> For that, two ſhall be one fleſh, <hi>veriùs intelligitur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, de Chriſto &amp; Eccleſiâ,</hi> hath its full truth in Chriſt and the Church: Now the reaſon why God would ſuffer this veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of fleſh conſigned to glory, fall into corruption, and not tranſlate it preſently as he was able, into corruption, may be thus gathered from his word. It ſtood with the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and power of the great Maker (all whoſe gifts are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) not to let that earthen veſſell which himſelfe had framed in the confines of ſpirituality, and now by the envy of the Devill was blemiſhed, to continue ever in that deformity; but rather to returne it into the lumpe, and mould it over againe; and this councell of the Almighty wee reade firſt foretold in the old Teſtament,<note place="margin">Jer. 18.6.</note> then fulfilled in the new. God is the Potter, and wee the clay, ſaith the ſame our <hi>Ieremy</hi> who propheſied of the buying of the Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:66448:6"/>
field,<note place="margin">Mat. 27.9.</note> when by the envyer of the Potter this veſſell was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, Ieſus Chriſt overcomming the Malignant defacer, purchaſed of God with the price of his owne bloud the moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding againe of the Veſſell which he had redeemed from the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy: Wherefore he gave us a manifeſt tryall in his owne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which though he ſuffered to dye to purchaſe the remaking of all the reſt; yet it (as it needed no new molding for any ſtaine, and to be returned into the lumpe, ſo) could not be held of death, nor ſee corruption. So the grave is the Potters field, purchaſed with Chriſts bloud, and burying the placing of the ſhivered veſſell in Godslimbeck, to be new caſt, when he ſhall with fire calcine the whole maſſe of the world, <hi>&amp; carnis au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum è limi ſordibus excuſato cenſu eliquabit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian,</hi> alluding to that of <hi>Malachy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 3.17.</note> And they ſhall be mine in the day when I make up my jewels.</p>
            <p>Therefore, my beloved Brethren, be ſtedfaſt, unmovea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, alwaies abounding in every worke of the Lord, and duty of devotion: foraſmuch as you know your labour is not in vaine in the Lord, but what is done herein to the Body is not Bodily, but Spirituall, and full of glorious hope; as if your now departing ſoule ſhould whiſper thus to the Body, feare not deare ſiſter, our inſtant ſeperation, nor thy folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſſolution: I know that our Redeemer liveth, and I have intruſted him with thee; ſo that he is both a Proprietary, and a D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>poſitary, and by this my laſt Teſtament I bequeath thee to him, <hi>who with his owne bloud purchaſed of the great Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thy reparation, and whom the God of Peace brought againe from the dead by the bloud of the everlaſting Teſtament:</hi> I know whom I have truſted, and I am perſwaded that he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to keepe thee whom I have committed unto him againſt that day.</p>
            <p>Wee have learn'd from the Text that Religious mourning, and decent buriall are to be performed to every Chriſtian, and that ſorrow and death continue, after Noah, a generall inunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion we finde, in that <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſiah</hi> dyed, and <hi>Jeremiah</hi> lamented.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Jeremiah lamented.</hi> Obſerve how the ſpirit of God dwels upon, and delights in enlarging this Teſtimony: what
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:66448:6"/>
an honourable Crowne of ſuffrages encompaſſeth this, <hi>Jeremiah lamented.</hi> Firſt imediately before the Text, the tide of teares brake in upon Hieruſalem; then ſurrounded Juda, then over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowed all Judah and Hieruſalem, <hi>univerſus Juda, &amp; Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem luxerunt:</hi> yet ſtill the floud ſwells, and with it the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the ſpirit of God moving upon the ſad face of the waters, and <hi>Jeremiah lamented:</hi> as if all the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer teares had beene in <hi>Jeremiah's</hi> teares drown'd, crown'd, wept over againe. Then preſently after the Text (for, like a Sepia, <hi>Jeremiah</hi> deales his black dole round about him) firſt all the ſinging men and the ſinging women, the whole quire, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicant, reſownd <hi>Jeremiah's</hi> epicediall anthemes: further they made them an ordinance in Iſraell, theſe pious Homilies are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to both Kingdomes by an Eccleſiaſticall conſtitution: can there be any more yet? yea, <hi>Ecce ſcripta ſunt,</hi> Behold they are written in the Lamentations, recorded, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by the ſpirit of God as his owne: made part of Gods word; ſo that we may ſay, to this day God laments for the King by <hi>Jeremiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jeremiah lamented,</hi> one of the Prieſts,<note place="margin">Jer. 1.1.</note> of the ſonnes of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron: <hi>ſacerdos è ſacerdotibus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Hierome,</hi> to whoſe holy order Gods owne word made it a prophanation to mourne for the dead:<note place="margin">Levit 21.1.</note> upon the death of the King the divine Law admits a prohibition; upon ſuch an occaſion the head uſed to ſacred unction, is bedowed with teares, and the water hath got above the oile, thus <hi>Jeremiah</hi> the Prieſt <hi>lamented.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jeremiah lamented,</hi> the Prophet, the egregious Prophet,<note place="margin">Jer. 1.5.10.</note> ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified in the wombe, knowne before formed, ſet over the Nations and Kingdomes to root out and pull downe, to build and to plant. This <hi>Jeremiah</hi> the Prophet <hi>lamented.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ieremiah</hi> had oft had juſt cauſe to mourne for himſelfe:<note place="margin">v. 8.</note> in the 20 chapter I cryed out, I cryed, violence and ſpoile: becauſe the word of the Lord was made a reproach to me, and a diri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion dayly. In the 18 chapter they ſaid come, let us diviſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices againſt Jeremie, let us ſmite him with the tongue.<note place="margin">v. 18.</note> In the 37 chapter, he was apprehended and accuſed of treaſon,<note place="margin">v. 15.</note> and falling away to the enemies of the State, and thereupon
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:66448:7"/>
ſmitten and caſt into the dungeon: yet all this writ him not in the black letter, and great charactet of a Lamenter; but now ſome occaſion hath preſented it ſelfe, that by the penne of the ſpirit of God chronicles him a Lamenter to all poſterities. O Lord what is done that thy Jeremie, <hi>(quid ruus Æneas?)</hi> thy owne Jeremie,<note place="margin">Jer. 25.15.</note> whom thou appointedſt, to give the cup of thy fury into the hands of all Nations, muſt now himſelfe drinke it up, and againe fill it with eyes, and with thoſe lips empty it againe? as the Canaanites ſaid of Joſephs mourning for his Father Iſraell:<note place="margin">Gen. 50.11.</note> this is a grievous mourning to the Egyptians: this is ſuch a catycliſme of teares that to finde the object of them, and obſerve the ſwelling of this Nilus whoſe head yet lies higher) we muſt ſearch higher then the Prophet himſelfe: and higher then the Prophet himſelfe if we will ſearch, we muſt mount up to a paramount; for ſo are we directed by him that was himſelfe both King and Prophet: know ye not, <hi>quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam Princeps,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 3.38.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; maximus,</hi> that a Prince, and he the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, is fallen this day in Iſraell? would then Gyant ſorrow finde a fit object? aſcend above the Prophet to the King: would it have a fit mouth to expreſſe it ſelfe? Returne from the King to the Prophet: So as the oyle on both their heades is above all liquors, ſorrow becomes ſuperlative, both for matter and manner, lamentation in her exaltation, both for ſubject and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; <hi>Ieremiah</hi> and <hi>Ioſiah:</hi> All mourne but as <hi>Hierome</hi> reades it, <hi>Ieremias maximè,</hi> and juſtly, <hi>maxime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro maximo,</hi> The King is dead, and the Prophet muſt be chiefe Mourner at the Funerall: 'Tis his place. 'tis his portion, 'tis his honour; ſtand back pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vulgars, make roothe for <hi>Ieremiahs</hi> ſorrow: Pull all thoſe blubberd papers off the Herſe. Heere's one ſhort endleſſe Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphe, <hi>Ieremiah</hi> lamented for <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> the Prieſt and the Prophet for the King.</p>
            <p>Indeed there is ſuch a ſympathy and continuation of nature betwixt King and Prieſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 77.20.</note> that <hi>David</hi> acknowledged but one hand in <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron;</hi> of <hi>ancient Pontificium capitis</hi> was the Kings, and <hi>Pectorale judicii</hi> the Prieſts: From the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Diadema,</hi> and the <hi>Inſula,</hi> the Crowne, and the Miter were ſwadled together in the <hi>primogeniture,</hi> which neceſſity,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:66448:7"/>
and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is expreſſed by the ſame Hebrew word <hi>Cohen,</hi> ſignifying both King and Prieſt, and though by neceſſary diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation in this world this kindred of Unctions obtaine in moſt places ſeverall ſtations and officials; yet wee both enjoy now ſpiritually,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.9.</note> and expect eternally heereafter a reunion of both a Royall Prieſthood, a Kingdome of Prieſts: In the meane time God hath neither committed the people to a King onely in a ſecular care,<note place="margin">Exod. 19 6.</note> nor to the Prieſt onely to be catechiſed in the principles, and taught the Myſteries of Divinity; but the King is to provide them meanes, and keepe them to the uſe thereof to their ſupreme felicity, and the Prieſt to direct them to diſcharge thoſe offices and actions, which in other men are meerely morally good, in order to the ſame eternall capacity, and upon default, <hi>durum judicium erit his qui praeſunt,</hi> ſaith <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wiſd. 6.6.</note> ſharpe judgement ſhall be to them that are in high pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Wherefore whether in Gods juſt chaſtiſments, or mens unjuſt oppoſition; the King and the Prieſt are like Hypocrates twinnes, both joy and grieve together: ſo Jeremie in this Lamentation,<note place="margin">Lament. 2.6.</note> God hath rejected in his indignation the King and the Prieſt, and Hoſee of the other Kingdome,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 3.4.</note> Iſraell ſhall abide many dayes without a King and a Prince, and an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phode: at once Moſes had his Dathan, and Aaron his Chorah: at once Hieruſalem her Samaria, and the Temple it Dan and Bethel: the anoynted heads have ſuch a ſymbolicall quality, that like Gods owne Harpſtrings equally tuned, and ſet to one another, the one cannot be ſtruck but the other ſhakes; ye cannot touch his Anointed and doe his Prophets no harme: whereupon their grand and leading enemy, ſtrains himſelfe and puts to all his force (as Samſon did) to pull downe at once the two pillars of the State the King, and the Prieſt, as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that when there is no King in Iſraell, then there is no open viſion, but the word of God is precious even in the multitude of Micah's Jonathans. Juſtly then, if the King be either natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally dead, as Joſiah here, or civilly, and unnaturally, as Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid by Abſolom, the Prophet is he that muſt Lament, when the breath of the noſtrils is gone, what is the breath of the mouth but a groane?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:66448:8"/>Did then Jeremiah's ſorrow looke through Joſiah, as wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters runne through pipes to waters, to that cloude which upon this ſun-ſet muſt obſcure his Office, and dignity? indeede our firſt parents, covering themſelves with leaves, taught their children ſo to plume their yas thoughts before they let them fly abroade, that our complaints for the moſt part looke at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers when they aime at our ſelves: and this ſimulation of love and ſorrow none meet with ſo often as Kings, who therefore are often ſold, ſaid Diocletian, by their favourites: for their fortunes can eaſily exhale and exalt vapours (which ſomtimes turn to State terrifying comets) but their vertues cannot make them ſixt ſtarres: their dependance ſuddenly Creates crocodile friends, that weepe not out of love of the King, but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that looke upon the King as their benefactour, not as the publique good; for that requires a largeneſſe, and ſinglenes of heart: an heart not like the horſe-leech crying ever, give, give; but like a cleare glaſſe, which receiving the King as the light of Gods countenance, diffuſeth the beames all abroad, and improves the warmth to the common good: but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary contraction of heart comes from thoſe three which Paul rankes in the firſt file of the murraines of our times,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.2.</note> ſelfelove, coveteouſneſſe, and pride. The firſt two, ſelfelove, and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, adulterating the love, and abuſing the favour of the King: make way to the third, pride, to abolliſh hate of him, to induce hate, and to elevate reſpect, and to breed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of him, which is more dangerous then hate Now this ſhruken coldneſſe, and ſelfaiming hath ſo ſpred through the poyſon of the enemy of mankinde and order, that the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and large-hearted love of a King, as a King, is ſo rare <hi>(pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci Reges non regna colunt)</hi> that it may be reckond among <hi>Panci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rollus</hi> his <hi>vetera deperdita:</hi> but the reſiſting him, even to open warre, one of <hi>Goodwin's, nova reperta,</hi> yea from licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in contemning the perſon, this Luciferian infection is growne up to boldneſſe to contemne the profeſſion, Pride hath budded,<note place="margin">Ezech. 7.10.</note> ſaith <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> violence is riſen up into a rod of wickedneſſe. The Donatiſts in Conſtantine's time objected to the Orthodox Divines, <hi>Quid vobis cum Regibus terrae, quos
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:66448:8"/>
nunquam Christianitas niſi invides ſenſit?</hi> what have you to doe with the Kings of this world, who have ever beene ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to Chriſtianity? neither were they ſo confuted by <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi> but that the Cadmean progeny is revived in our age, <hi>faecunda vulpa ſaecula,</hi> when a curſed Nadab hath dared to throw this ſtrange fire from the Alter Damaſcenum upon our Alter, <hi>innatum est omnibus Regibus contrà Christum odium,</hi> all Kings beare an inbred hate to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the foxes that ſpoile our Vine,<note place="margin">Cant. 2.15. Rev. 9.3.</note> and our tender Grapes: theſe are the Locuſts that come, ſaith John, out of the bottomleſſe pit, and have no King,<note place="margin">Prov. 30.27.</note> ſaith yet go forth by bands. And certainely this ſelf-love, coveteouſneſſe, and pride (which corrupts the love to the perſon, and counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines to the authority of the King, and to do both, divides both) is a ſymtome of Gods rejection of a Kingdome, and the people. Breake an entire looking-graſſe, that one perfect face, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſhined in it while it was whole, appeares no more: but in place of it ſo many breaches, ſo many puppit phiſnomies ſtrive to repreſent the great face, and mock the ſight. <hi>Marcellinus</hi> obſerves that the glory of <hi>Rome</hi> began to retrograde when the great ones began to ſeeke every one his owne ends, and impropriate to himſelfe, <hi>hinc le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, &amp; plebiſcita, coactae, Et cum conſulibus turbantes jura Tribuni;</hi> ſo a private Tricipitina wrought a publique precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. The Prophet <hi>Hoſee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 10.3.1.</note> when he was to propheſie that now Iſraell ſhould ſay, I have no King, premiſed this diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Anarchie, Iſraell is an emptying Vine, that fructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies onely to it ſelfe, that doth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, luxuriate it ſelfe, but beares no fruit to the dreſſer: a people whoſe ſhoulders, like the Acephali, are aboue the face: ſee what the depravation, and deprivation of the love of a King can doe.</p>
            <p>On the contrary, the love of men to their King comes from him, by whom Kings raigne over men: this God imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted firſt by nature in that manifeſt impreſſion which the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique benefit of a King makes in all men, <hi>quantò diſcords liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate ſamentibus utilius ſit u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um eſſe, an ſerviant,</hi> ſaith <hi>Plinie,</hi> that it is better for men to be ſubject to one, then to be all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:66448:9"/>
jangling in untuned liberty: who is, ſaith <hi>Cyprian, pax populi, tutamen patriae, &amp;c.</hi> the peace of the people, the ſecurity of the Countrey, the immunity of the Commonalty, the joy of men: Wherefore before the Emperours gate in Rome was an Oake planted betwixt two Bay-trees; ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the felicity of the people depends upon the vertue and proſperity of the King. The Macedonians were ſenſible of this, who being put to ſlight by the Illyrians, ſent the next day for their Infant King into the field in his cradle, and then rallying their forces overthrew the Illyrians; ſhewing that the day before they wanted not valour, but a King; Even a dumbe man had conned this dictate of Nature ſo <hi>perquire,</hi> that ſeeing the King aſſaulted, he brake the ſtring of his tongue, and cryed out, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, If thou beeſt a man, doe not kill a King.</p>
            <p>Againe God confirmed this mandate of love to a King by the <hi>Magna Charta</hi> of his word (God ſpake once,<note place="margin">Pſal 62.11.</note> twice I heard it, once for the matter, twice for the manner) There went ſaith the ſacred Hiſtory,<note place="margin">Sam. 10.26.</note> with the King a band of men, whoſe hearts God had touched, but the children of <hi>Belial</hi> deſpiſed him who toucht their hearts?<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sam 9.20.</note> And on whom ſayd the Prophet to the King, is all the deſire of Iſrael; is it not on thee and thy Fathers houſe?<note place="margin">2 Sam. 21, 17.</note> The Iſraelits acknowledged to their King, thou art the light of Iſrael, thou art worth ten thouſand of us. And when the Spirit of God came upon the Generall of the Army of <hi>Iudah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 18.3.</note> he ſaid to the King, thine are wee <hi>David,</hi> and on thy ſide, thou Sonne of <hi>Ieſſe:</hi> Peace, peace be to thee, and peace be to thy helpers, for thy God helpeth thee. And leaſt yet <hi>Lucifers</hi> behaviour ſhould incarnate on earth (for ſome turbulent ſpirits, ſaith <hi>Calvine,</hi> count not Chriſts Kingdome advanced, nor themſelves at Chriſtian liberty, unleſſe they ſhake off all humane ſubjection) God hath coupled together and faſtned to his owne aſſertion the vindication of Kings, and joyned together his owne and their both love and deſpight. The Lord his God is with him,<note place="margin">Numb. 23.21.</note> and the ſhout of a King <hi>clangor victoriae Regis,</hi> is among them: who ſtrove againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> when they ſtrove againſt the Lord? And againe,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:66448:9"/>
their King ſhall paſſe before them, and the Lord on the head of them: But facing about, he curſed God and the King, was the high attaindure of any perſon, and the dire curſe of a Nation; they ſhall fret themſelves, and curſe their King and their God. Thus both Nature and Scripture injoyne and knit to the love of the true God, the true love of the King, even of <hi>Iulian</hi> the temporall Lord, ſaith <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> for the eternall Lords ſake. Nature in <hi>Eſops</hi> laſt charge to his Sonne <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, chvming to the Scripture <hi>Peters</hi> injunction to all Chriſtians, Feare God, Honour the King.</p>
            <p>Now if it be impiety not to mourne for their deaths, for whoſe lives it is iniquity not to pray, if <hi>Samuel</hi> mourned for a rejected King, and <hi>David</hi> told the Daughters of Iudah, of an evill King, that it was he that cloathed them with ſcarlet and delights, and put the Ornaments of gold upon their apparell; if the word of God that injoynes love of the living, juſtifie ſorrow for dying Kings <hi>(quod defles illud amaſti)</hi> How could the man whoſe eies were open which heard the words of God, which ſaw the viſion of the Almighty, who was not ignorant that a people is in better condition under an evill King, then without all government, who perceived that in their Kings untimely death, the Lord of Hoſtes called to weeping and mourning; who was both Prieſt and Prophet, how could he but lament for <hi>Ioſiah?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea lament he did, yea lament, <hi>&amp; auſus &amp; potuit,</hi> though <hi>Pharoah</hi> were in the Land yet warme with the Royall blood: Yea he durſt not but lament greatly; and profeſſe ſorrow for his Kings death, leaſt the peoples ſlighting or ſoone forgetting it might be imputed to his example (<hi>tali dedicatore noſtri gemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus gloriamur,</hi> but that rather they might ſay with <hi>Tertullian</hi> in the like caſe) his love rejoyceth in ſorrow, and triumphs in black, as the devotion of thoſe that preferred the pitty in bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Steven,</hi> before the feare of their owne lives. He durſt mourne for his King yea mourne he did for <hi>Ioſiah, tanquam pro unigenito,</hi> ſaith <hi>Zachary,</hi> as for an onely ſonne, <hi>tanquam pro primogenito,</hi> as for a firſt borne Sonne the mourning of Hada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drimmon
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:66448:10"/>
in the valley of Megiddo was like the mourning for the great ſhepheard, Chriſt, ſaith the ſame Zachary, Zach. 12.11. who now in Joſiahs death had broken both his ſtaves, Beauty and Bandes: For Joſiah, as for Jeſus: for Joſiah dying among them, as for Jeſus departing from them, <hi>pro Chriſto Domini, ac pro Chriſto Domino:</hi> Wherefore the Spirit of God, who enrolled in the booke of Jaſher, and bad teach the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Judah the ſtaves of Sauls funerall ſong called the Bow, hath alſo eternized among his owne dictated manuſcripts, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiahs lamentations for Ioſiah.</p>
            <p>In which Lamentations that particular (or rather generall) verſe, Lament. 4.20. The breath of our noſtrills, the Anointed of the Lord, was taken in their pits, may be called the nave of the wheele, whoſe ſeverall beames integrate that whole booke. Calvin upon this place taunts the reverend Hierom with groſſe errour, for ſaying that this booke of Lamentations was Ieremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs funerall ſong for Ioſiah; and addes, that the cited verſe is wreſted to Ioſiah: And yet the ſame Calvin himſelfe in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place of his Comments ſaith, in 12 Zach. 11. and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies it (againſt his owne expoſition upon the place) from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that <hi>Jeremias in hoc lugubri carmine reſpexit propriè ad Joſiam, ſicuti teſtatur ſacra hiſtoria,</hi> in this mournefull ſong did ayme properly at Ioſiah, as the holy Hiſtory of the Bible teſtifieth: Then coting particularly the foreſaid verſe, he adds, after Ioſiahs death (<hi>in cujus animâ vivebat anima populi,</hi> in whoſe ſoule the one ſoule of the people lived) that people was a meere carcaſe, and the taking away of Ioſiah was an evident ſigne of Gods wrath againſt them, and that Gods favour was extinct with that King, <hi>quia felicitas populi,</hi> becauſe the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of the people depended upon the King, <hi>&amp; Regia digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas,</hi> and the Regall Dignity was a ſure pledge of Gods favour to them.</p>
            <p>Thus this word, <hi>Joſiah is dead,</hi> was to Iudah another Icha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bod, where is the glory? The beauty of Iſrael is ſtayned by thy waters, O Megiddo: with Ioſiah, <hi>vale Lex, vale Moſes,</hi> farewell the Arke, farewell the milke and honey of the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Land: upon the ſetting of this Sunne the Manna in the pot
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:66448:10"/>
melts, the bloſſomes on Aarons red blaſt, and the Almonds be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come bitter Almonds: From Ioſiahs death the Prophet dates the fall of Hieruſalem. By the violation of Ioſiahs head Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem her ſelfe is become <hi>ſacrum caput</hi> and her Epitaphe is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared in this word, Ioſiah is dead, that is (as Chryſoſtome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundes that of the Angel to the bleſſed Virgine, Luke, 1.31. They ſhall call his name) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and the ſucceſſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhall finde and verifie that Ioſiah is dead. O Ieremy, would thou hadſt been onely a mourner here and not a Prophet; but I finde thee no where more a Prophet then in mourning heere. The Prophet knew that in Gods pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Hieruſalem was now <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, devoted to ruine, that the Temple was already demoliſhed in her patterne in the Mount, that the Angels had deſerted the Sanctuary, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were caſheered in the High Counſell in Heaven; yet was it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for deploring Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Temple, Sanctuary, people &amp; all, to lament one Ioſiah, even divine providence ſo diſpoſing that ſo pretious an head ſhould not be violate till God had rejected the whole body, Luke, 23.31. <hi>ſi haec in viridi, quid fiet in aridâ;</hi> if this be done in the greene tree, what ſhall become of the dry one? Needes muſt the people be outlawed, when their King is thus rapt from them, in whom they had truely <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as Plato ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, whoſe arme was a meaſure, and whoſe religious minde was a Law to them; and what but epidemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call death could be expected, when the devotion of ſo zealous an head could kindle no fire in the paraliticall body: He that delivered Abrahams Couzen, vexed with the filthy converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Sodomites, 2 Pet. 2.7. knew how to deliver Davids owne, and reſerve a rebellious Generation to emminent judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Wherefore to the ſoule of Ioſiah the Angel called, as once to Lot the husband, Gen. 19 22. Eſcape thou and flye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to bright Zoar, the mountaine of the viſion of God, and leave thy unbelieving wife (who of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is become <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) to be made to all Nations a monument of rejecting the Law, and not hearkning to her King and husband; what pane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giriques would the heathen (who knew not God, onely had naturall love of loyalty and vertue) have made, had they had a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:66448:11"/>
King that would have ſuffered loſſe of power, eſtate, glory, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, wife and children; yea whatſoever ſtupified Subjects prefer before a King, rather then conſent to the prophaning of Gods ſervice, and the enſlaving the perſons and eſtates of his people; nothing could make their miſery more miſerable, nor more convict them of their rebellion, then that their beſt King was made their laſt. Indeed this honour was due to Ioſiahs pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and this ſolace to his Funerals that none ſhould ſucceed him, whom none could ſecond, and that by the ſequell of Ioſiahs death all Kingdomes might learne how much the weale of a State depends upon the life, and how cloſe the ruine of it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes upon the want of a religious King: All were defective ſaith the ſonne of Syrach, but David, Hezechiah, and Ioſiah. Our Poſterity will reade a Chronicle of England, not Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phall, that will make them as much wonder at us, as admire the ſtory; till this day all were defective but Elizabeth, Iames, and Charles, when of three vertuous and religious Kings, the third is untimely taken away, the people that by having the two firſt would not learne to appretiate a King, are by the loſſe of the third taught what it is to have none. Daughters of Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, Ieremy weepes not for Ioſiah, but weepes for you and your children; for ſinne the Mother, and deſolation the broode, leſt the dayes come, leſt the lamentable dayes come, in which they ſhall ſay, bleſſed are the Inhabitants that have no poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the parents that are not indebted to children for edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p>The Spirit of God teſtifieth heere the blood of Ioſiah, and the teares of Ieremiah, to the end that the people ſhould trace the teares of the Prophet through the bloud of the King; firſt to their owne impending puniſhment, and thence to their paſt ſinnes: For if you looke, O Daughtet of Iudah to the acts of Jeremiah himſelfe, he had already lived long, if to your owne aggravation of wrath, too long; if to your neede of ſuch a King to ſtand in the gap, he dyed too ſoone, if to the honour of his owne remembrance he ſhall never dye, but all Poſterities ſhall copie out from Joſiah.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:66448:11"/>
            <q>
               <l>Compoſitum vis faſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> animi, ſanctoſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> receſſus</l>
               <l>Mentis, &amp; in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>octum generoſo pectus honeſto.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And the remembrance of Joſiah ſhall be like the compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the perfume made by the art of the Apothecary, ſweet as honey in all mouthes, as muſick at a banquet of wine, Eccleſ. 49.1. For that name that entred before his mortall life, goes not out with it and that which attended not for his birth, will not waite on his death: But as it was impoſed by Propheticall breath, ſo in Propheticall teares it is embalmed, and continued to all Poſterities, which ſhall wonder and be amazed (even the Kings of the earth and all the Inhabitants of the world, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. 4.12.) and not believe that the enemy could have entred the ports of the Daughter of Zion, having ſo religious a King, under whoſe ſhadow they lived ſecurely among the Heathen, Lament 4.20. But hearing withall that this King was ſo taken away, they ſhall acknowledge that the God of Iſrael dealt therein with that people and Joſiah in the ſame manner as he dealt once with David and them, 2 Sam. 24 1. He that ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red David to ſinne in numbring the people, for the ſinne of a number whom he would deſtroy, ſuffering alſo Joſiah, ſo zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for the Law and the weale of the people, to goe againſt the word in the mouth, and fall by the ſword in the hand of Necho, 2 Chron. 35, 22. That the Bulwarke which ſtood in the way of the deſtroyer once broken downe, the floud of the wrath of God, <hi>quâ data porta ruat,</hi> might thenceforth breake in upon a rebellious Nation, that ſo they might be puniſhed by his death, who was ſuffered to ſlip for their puniſhment, and by whoſe righteous life they would not be reformed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> As for that one act of Joſiahs going to war, againſt Pharoh, piety for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids us to thinke that Ioſiah would have done it, had he beene forbidden by the mouth of Ieremiah, or any of Gods Prophets. But in the mouth of Pharoah what more authority could this interdiction expect from Ioſiah, then that commination from the mouth of Zenacherib obtained of Hezekiah; 2 King. 18.25. Indeede wee who now have the ſtory written ſince by the holy Ghoſt reade that Ioſiah hearkned not to the word of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho from the mouth of God, 2 Chron. 35.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. But if this
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:66448:12"/>
were a ruine (and ſuch an one was Moſes his at the waters of Meribah, ſo ſubtile that it muſt be a quick eye can diſcerne it) wee may ſay with Gregory, <hi>pro qualitatibus ſubditorum diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponuntur acta regentium;</hi> the actions of Kings are (by Gods permiſſion and overruling hand) diſpoſed according to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert of their Subjects, <hi>justus interim Judex, &amp;c.</hi> In the meane time the juſt Iudge vindicates thoſe ſinnes of the King at their hands, for whoſe ſake he was ſuffered to ſlip: Heere the ſinne of Iudah came to it height, in their greater guiltineſſe of his leſſer ſinne. Their ſinne had it complement in his ſlip, and their puniſhment it beginning from his death. O the juſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearcheable judgements of the great King: From this judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wee are taught how ſacred a relation is betwixt a King and his people; ſo ſtrong, ſo neare is it, that he that atempts to part them, had better halfe cleave a great Oake, and forcing the ſides to open, ſtand betwixt them at their ſuddaine clapping together againe: See the piety of this potent relation on the Kings part in Moſes, Exod. 32.32. O forgive the ſinne of this people, or elſe blot me out of the booke thou haſt written: See it in David, what have theſe ſheepe done? Let thy hand be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon me and my fathers houſe, 2 Sam. 24.17. On the Subjects part, how ſtrong and indelible this naturall love to their King is (though indeede the wife be more ſubject to the tempter) wee reade in thoſe ſenſitive creatures, in which <hi>Rege incolumi mous omnibus una<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> amiſſo rupere fidem,</hi> in naturall men, which upon the violent death of their King (even after a good ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour was poſſeſſed) have never reſted till the doers were puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, as in Domitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome have died for pitty to their King, as in Otho and the beſt, <hi>Optimus,</hi> Emperor executed that which Ner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va coted to him out of Homer, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But where the knowledge of God was, this zeale was ever more warme. The people ſayd to Samuel, who is he that ſayd Saul ſhall not raign over us? Bring the men that wee may put them to death, 1 Sam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. And the ſame people that were deluded by Abſolom to rebell againſt David their King, after the fit was over, were ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ealous for him, that they were at ſtrife through all the Tribes of Iſrael, who ſhould be firſt in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:66448:12"/>
bringing back the King, and expiating their raſh folly with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubled Loyalty, 2 Sam. 19.42.</p>
            <p>The ſtrength of this relation is the reaſon that: God ſometimes puniſheth a King for the peoples ſake, as heere in Ioſiah, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the people for the Kings ſake, as in Saule, 2 Sam. 21.1. And ſometimes lets the King tranſgreſſe, that he may puniſh the people, as in David, 2 Sam. 24.1. This ſolemne courſe of Almighty God in puniſhing is the ſtrength of the current of Jeremiahs Lamentations for Ioſiah; ſo drawing, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the people from that one act of Ioſiah to conſideration of their paſt ſinnes, and from the death of Ioſiah to their preſent judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo to God himſelfe.</p>
            <p>And this is the <hi>decumanus fluctus;</hi> now have teares ſwelled to their Land-marke, ſpringing from ſorrow for common death, and vulgar mourners to the chiefe mourner the Prophet, and the hyperocall ſorrow for a King; then riſing from the death of a King, to the loſſe of a Ioſiah, thence to the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent of the loſſe it diffuſeth, then ſwelleth againe to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture of the great ſhepheard, thence paſſeth to the motive cauſe of all theſe, ſinne. At laſt it mounts up to the efficient and diſpoſer, Almighty God: So our Ieremy in this Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for Ioſiah, Lament. 3.42.39 Wee have tranſgreſſed and rebelled, and thou haſt not pardoned; and againe, wherefore doth a living man murmure, a man, for the puniſhment of his ſinne? For even thoſe, whom God hath forſaken, grieve at their puniſhment (they have not cryed to me with their heart, when they howled upon their beds, ſaith Hoſee, Hoſ. 7.14) but this is a ſigne that the party under puniſhment is yet a man, a live man,, when the ſoule ſtumbles not, and ſtops either mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring at the puniſhment, or at the ſecond cauſe quarrelling; but leaping over and riſing above both ſecond cauſes and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, aſcends to God, arguing thus with our Ieremy in this Lamentation, Lament. 3.37 Who is he that ſaith it, and it comes to paſſe, when the Lord commandeth it not? Out of the mouth of the moſt high proceedes not evill and good: Thus perſuing our ſinnes to God, wee finde in him both judgement and mercy; judgement by which he hath (but from us) to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:66448:13"/>
mercy, in which he hath (of his <hi>ſeminarium miſerecordia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi>) to be gratious, and repent him of the evill, upon the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils repentance. 2 Cor. 1.3. Whereas if wee ſtay in our affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, either out of dulneſſe or impatience at the ſecond cauſes and inſtruments, by higher preſſures, wee become hardened, and dejected by greater; moreover in the men that oppreſſe us, wee ſhall finde onely inſultation and matter of provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is my complaint ſaith Iob, Iob <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>1, 4. to man, if it were ſo, how ſhould not my ſpirit be troubled? And David, let me fall into the hands of the Lord, for great are his mercies: but let me not fall into the hand of man, 1 Chron. 22.13. And our Ieremy in this Lamentation, Lament. 3.21.22. This I recall to minde, therefore I have hope, it is of the Lords mercy that wee are not conſumed, becauſe his compaſſions faile not.</p>
            <p>Upon this apprehenſion of both judgement and mercy in God Ieremy was comforted, and expreſſed it in this Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that wee through patience and comfort of the Scripture may have hope, the ſame word Littenoth ſignifies both Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and conſolation; for comfort takes beſt from one that laments with us, and he condoles truely that uſeth all meanes to comfort: I called upon thy name O Lord, and thou didſt heare my voice, Lament. 3.53.54.55.56.57.58. Thou drew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt neere in that day, and ſayedſt, when I called feare not, O Lord thou haſt pleaded the cauſes of my ſoule, thou haſt redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med my life. Thou haſt redeemed, obſerve Ieremy, that lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the loſſe of Ioſiah his King, was comforted in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Jeſus his Redeemer.</p>
            <p>Thus the ſoule, having at laſt wrought up to Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, findeth there mercy alſo And in this mercy of God meetes againe with the great Shepheard that had deſerted it, and from this ſhepheard obtaines grace, both to repent of it owne ruine (which offended God and blancht the ſhepheard) and to judge charitably of others in the ſame condition: By which grace it proceedes to patience, both to endure the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent affliction and to waite for deliverance, Heb. 11.35. (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preſent deliverance, or a better reſurrection, Mat. 12.20.) when and in what manner, the wiſdome of God ſhall (by ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:66448:13"/>
forth judgement unto victory upon impenitent ſinners, and the Sonne of righteouſneſſe with healing to contrite hearts) worke out the redemption, Mal. 4.2.</p>
            <p>The end, beloved, of every Text wee preach to you is, that you winde your ſelves into the truth it holds forth: And the aime of this my preſent Text is, that you conforme your ſelves to it celeſtiall ſemblance. To be ſelfe centred is earthly and ſenſuall; but to move for the publick good is heavenly and ſpirituall: If therefore there be any fellowſhip of the ſpirit, ſaith Paul, 2 Philip. 4. Looke not every one on his owne things, but on the things of others; for by embracing this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as Ignatius ſpeakes, this true gallantry of harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious love (while every one ſeekes the good and bewailes the evill of every one) a private evill is ſo divided, that it is heavy to no man, and a particular good ſo communicated, that it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doundes to all. Now, he that will ſeeke the good of all, muſt obſerve the courſe which he takes who rules all (heere our Text requires conformity to an higher heaven then the materiall) and diffuſe as he diffuſeth, elſe he may confound when he thinkes to communicate. And wee read that God led his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, while he delighted in them, by the hand of Moſes and Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron: But that in his diſpleaſure, the Sunne, the greater light is turned into blood, and the leſſer, the Moone into water, Pſ. 77.20. Wee have heere the ſpirit of God teſtifying, in Joſiah dying and Ieremiah crying,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Parumnè ad vos,</hi> ſaid Ieremy in this Lamentation, Lament. 1.12. (as leaving this bridge for Poſterity to paſſe from Iudah to England) Is it nothing to you? Yea our Syon may aſſelfe the words and go on with them: Behold and ſee, <hi>ſi major eſt ullus dolor quam dolor meus,</hi> that leſſer is all other ſorrow then my ſorrow: I have had ſucceſſively (I would, I could ſay ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully) three religious, vertuous, orthodox Princes, <hi>Elizabeth, James</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and <hi>Charles.</hi> I had a glorious face of a Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a Church, the very eye and excellency of all other Churches. In Henry the 7. by my King I was freed from the diviſion of Roſes, bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer then wormewood, ſharper then the thiſtle: In Henry 8. I ſhaked off by my King the Eccleſiaſticall Tyranny of Anti-chriſt:
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:66448:14"/>
In Edward 6. purity of Religion ſprang up with my King, which though it was watred with the bloud of Martyrs under Mary, that ſiſter without breaſts; yet grew it the more glorious under thoſe my three envies of all Kingdomes, Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, Iames, and Charles: But now <hi>facta eſt in pace amaritudo mea amariſſima</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> may I ſay with the ſick Hezekiah, behold upon my peace is come great bitterneſſe, Eſay 38.17. My bitterneſſe was great in the oppoſition of Hereticks, greater in the death of my children, the Martyrs; but now in my peace my bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is become greateſt, by the deſolation of my deareſt chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, the King and the Prophet. Of whom ſince God had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed me, Zach. 6.13. The counſell of peace ſhall be betwixt them both; I ſayd with my ſelfe, as Iob did, I ſhall dye in my neſt, my bow ſhall be renewed in my hand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Iob 29 18.30.26. But when I lookt for light, <hi>eruperunt tenebrae,</hi> then darkeneſſe ſurpriſed me; Ægyptian darkeneſſe, my waters were turned into bloud, &amp; my Land brought forth frogs in my Kings cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; palpable darkeneſſe; not onely ſuch as learned judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments can diſcerne, but ſuch as all hands but the actours feele and tremble at.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Parumnè ad vos</hi> (turning againe for the people) is it nothing to you? is the caſe of Ioſiah ſo lamented by Ieremiah nothing to you? Ier. 5.31. Doe my people love to have it ſo? And what will you doe in the end thereof? Shall that of Ioſiah be verified in you? Eſay. 26.11. Lord when thy hand is lifed up, they will not ſee, but they ſhall ſee. They will not ſee that the guilt proceeds from them; but they ſhall ſee that the judgement runs to them They will not ſee that the judgement lookes at them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> while it is ſnatching at the Crowne, and the Ephod; but they ſhal ſee it and be aſtoniſht, when (thoſe being taken away) it ſhall ſeize on them irrecoverably. This <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by whatſoever ſiniſter paſſages and tumults it makes now an eddy at the King and Prophet, will winde about againe, and with a crooked turne empty direct judgement elſewhere. It is your glory, that as the vindication of God and the King, the ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the King and the Prophet; ſo the welfare and ruine of the people and the King make up a trinity of combinations,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:66448:14"/>
a threefold corde that cannot be broken: If you ſerve the Lord and not rebell againſt his word, both you and your King ſhall be nigh unto the Lord your God; but if you doe wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, you ſhall be conſumed both you and your King, ſaid Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el to the deſirers of change of Government.</p>
            <p>Beloved, if that conformity to the celeſtiall ſemblance of the Text (in being every one <hi>in commune bonus,</hi> good not to himſelfe alone, but to the publique, in his private calling) would ſatisfie the whole end of the Text and our preſent caſe, I could diſmiſſe you with a compendious method of that duty; namely that (ſince every mans civill activity cannot extend ſo largely) his devotion may come home to every mans doore, to his Sonnes, and his Daughters, to his Garners, his ſheepe and oxen, to his peace and tranquillity, yea to his diſpoſure to the Lord his God; For all this is done by praying for the King. This were enough in a compoſed State, but it is not ſo with me, ſayd Job once, Iob 9.35. The greateſt of all the men of the Eaſt, and our Syon now, my Crowne is caſt to the ground, and the Sunne is gone downe upon my Prophets. Mic. 3.6.</p>
            <p>Therefore when the foundations are caſt downe, what ſhall the righteous doe? As he propoundes our caſe who had expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of it, and he addes the reſolution, the Lord is in his holy Temple, the Lords Throne is in Heaven, Pſalm. 11.3.4. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Symetry of the partes; on earth foundations in the plurall, the King and the Prieſt; but unity in the patterne in Heaven the Lord, yet (in proportion to the building on earth) expreſſed likewiſe as in the plurall, the Temple and the Throne. If then you would have your dayes on earth as the dayes of Heaven, as Moſes exhorted the Iſraelites, Deut. 11.21. Doe as he commandeth in whom Heaven and Earth are revealed and reconciled. Render to Caeſar, and render to God, Math. 22, 21. Heere's both Caeſar propounded and God, and yet but one <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; yea and firſt it is ſayd to Caeſar: For of the good wee can render to God, Caeſar is the Miniſter to us, and what obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience wee render to Caeſar is rendred to God as the termina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive object. After all the rendring to Caeſar there remaines a rendring to God, and in all the rendring to Caeſar there is a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:66448:15"/>
rendring to God. Render therefore to Caeſar, and render to God, <hi>ſed &amp; ipſum Caeſarem reddite Deo,</hi> but reſtore Caeſar himſelfe to God; as he is a foundation reſtore him to God by acknowledging him to be from God, as he is a ſhaken founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, reſtore him to God, to the ſervice that God hath ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him for, and to the meanes to performe the ſame: For you owe to the patterne in Heaven (and through the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on earth muſt render) <hi>juſtitiam Throno, Templo preces,</hi> juſtice to the Throne, prayers to the Temple; the Throne in Heaven requires of you juſtice too, and the Temple in Heaven prayers for the King on earth. <hi>Diſcite juſtitiam moniti, &amp; non tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere Divos.</hi> Take heede Subjects, how you deale with Kings, he that muſt judge betwixt you is a King, not a Subject. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore then to God his King, leſt you be like thoſe Gyants, the Aloades, that ſacrificed to their God Mars, and yet fettred his hands. Let us conclude with our Ieremy, and his Lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Lament 5. verſ. 21.22. <hi>Turne us unto thee, O Lord, and wee ſhall be turned; renew our dayes as of old, unleſſe thou haſt utterly rejected us, and caſt the nice upon us.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Gloria Deo &amp; Chriſto.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:66448:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
